<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Rish&#39;s AI Notes</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Rish&#39;s AI Notes</description>
    <image>
      <title>Rish&#39;s AI Notes</title>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/blog/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.139.4</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 01:06:38 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Maximum Likelihood Estimation and Loss Functions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/posts/ml_estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 01:06:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/posts/ml_estimation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I started learning about loss functions, I could always understand the intuition behind them. For example, the mean squared error (MSE) for regression seemed logical—penalizing large deviations from the ground-truth makes sense. But one thing always bothered me: I could never come up with those loss functions on my own. Where did they come from? Why do we use these specific formulas and not something else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This frustration led me to dig deeper into the mathematical and probabilistic foundations of loss functions. It turns out, the answers lie in a concept called Maximum Likelihood Estimation (MLE). In this blog, I’ll take you through this journey, showing how these loss functions are not arbitrary but derive naturally from statistical principles. I&amp;rsquo;ll start by defining what Maximum Likelihood Estimation (MLE) is, followed by the intricate connection between Maximum Likelihood Estimation (MLE) and Kullback-Leibler (KL) divergence. To conclude this article, I show how loss functions like Mean Squared Error loss and Binary Cross Entropy can be derived from Maximum Likelihood estimation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
